Guide to the Ethan Allen Hitchcock Collection on Indian Removal
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Ethan Allen Hitchcock collection on Indian removal
1804-1896
WA MSS S-2678
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.05
(5 boxes)
The collection documents several episodes in the history of Indian removal in the southeastern United States and Missouri, focusing on the activities of Generals Ethan Allen Hitchcock and Thomas Sidney Jesup in the 1830s and early 1840s. Material includes autograph letters, signed, and manuscript reports, diaries, and maps.
Hitchcock, Ethan Allen, 1798-1870
Jesup, Thomas Sidney, 1788-1860
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from various sources, 1963-1994, as noted in the description of each acquisition.
Custodial History
The custodial history of material described here is not entirely known. Notes that accompany some acquisitions indicate that Ethan Allen Hitchcock collected documentation relating to the Creek War of 1836, to the Second Seminole War, and to Indian removal campaigns generally. In order to facilitate research on Hitchcock's activities relating to Indian removal, the Beinecke Library has described several acquisitions of topically related material as a collection.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Ethan Allen Hitchcock (1798-1870)
Ethan Allen Hitchcock was born in Vergennes, Vermont in 1798. He graduated from the United States Military Academy in 1817 and was a career Army officer. He served in the Second Seminole War, the Mexican-American War, and the Civil War. A philosopher and scholar, he published several monographs, including Remarks Upon Alchemy and the Alchemists (1857), Swedenborg: A Hermetic Philosopher (1858), and Christ the Spirit (1860). His memoirs are collected in A Traveler in Indian Territory: The Journal of Ethan Allen Hitchcock (Cedar Rapids, Ia., The Torch Press,1930).
Scope and Contents
The collection documents several episodes in the history of Indian removal in the Southeastern United States, focusing on the activities of Generals Ethan Allen Hitchcock and Thomas Sidney Jesup in the 1830s and early 1840s. Material includes autograph letters, signed, and manuscript reports, diaries, and maps.
Arrangement
Organized into five groupings: 1963 Acquisition, 1964 Acquisition, 1986 Acquisition, 1992 Acquisitions, 1994 Acquisition.
Cherokee Indians; Choctaw Indians; Creek Indians; Creek War, 1836; Generals -- United States; Indian agents; Indian Removal, 1813-1903; Indians of North America -- Alabama; Indians of North America -- Florida; Indians of North America -- Georgia; Indians of North America -- Missouri; Indians of North America -- Oklahoma; Indians of North America -- Government relations; Indians of North America -- Treaties; Indians of North America -- Wars -- 1815-1875; Seminole Indians; Seminole War, 2nd, 1835-1842; Soldiers -- United States; Alabama; Florida; Fort Gibson (Okla.); Fort Wayne (Ind.); Georgia; Missouri; Oklahoma; Southern States; United States -- History -- 1815-1861; Generals -- United States; Indian agents -- 19th century; Soldiers -- United States -- 19th century; Cogswell, Jonathan; Harris, Carey A.; Hitchcock, Ethan Allen, 1798-1870; Jesup, Thomas Sidney, 1788-1860; Osceola, Seminole chief, 1804-1838; Spencer, John C. (John Canfield), 1788-1855; United States. Army ( Military life); United States. Office of Indian Affairs
- 1963 Acquisition, 1837-1839; 0.21; (1 box)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Purchased by Frederick W. Beinecke for the Western Americana Collection, from Edward Eberstadt & Sons, Catalogue 161 (item 56), 1963.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  The acquisition consists of Ethan Allen Hitchcock correspondence, chiefly letters to Commissioner of Indian Affairs Carey A. Harris. The correspondence relates to the removal of Indians from Missouri Territory, treaties, conflicts between the military and the Office of Indian Affairs, appropriations by Congress, delay in remittances and inaccurate accounts, padded muster rolls, transportation of goods, and the possible transfer of Hitchcock.
  Other correspondents include Alfred Bronson, J. Hartley Crawford, Charles Findlay, Lucy Hitchcock, Stephen Watts Kearny, William D. McKissack, F. Pfister, J. T. Sprague, Joshua Pilcher, M.M. Vineyard, and Major Wade.
  Accompanied by a calender list.
  General note
  Former call number: WA MSS S-947
  - Ethan Allen Hitchcock correspondence, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ethan Allen Hitchcock correspondence, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Ethan Allen Hitchcock correspondence, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 1964 Acquisition, 1842
  Purchased from Edward Eberstadt on the Beinecke No. 1 Fund, 1964.
  The acquisition consists of letters from Ethan Allen Hitchcock to John Canfield Spencer in 1842, when Hitchcock was stationed at Fort Wayne, Indiana. The correspondence relates to the ill treatment of Indians by soldiers, and justification of the Cherokee claims of insufficient rations and funds. In addition Hitchcock advises the abandonment of Fort Wayne as it has outlived its usefulness.
  Former call number: WA MSS S-1068
  - Ethan Allen Hitchcock Letters to John Canfield Spencer, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 1986 Acquisition, 1836-1842; 0.24; (1 box)
  Purchased from Goodspeed's Book Shop, Inc., on the Library Associates Fund, 1986.
  The acquisition consists of a diary by Thomas Sidney Jesup, and letters from Ethan Allen Hitchcock to Major Samuel Cooper and to Secretary of War John C. Spencer.
  General Thomas Sidney Jesup's "Diary of Events Etc. in the Creek Campaign" relates Jesup's experience in the campaign to remove the Creeks from Alabama in 1836.
  Letters from Ethan Allen Hitchcock in Fort King and Tampa Bay, Florida to Major Samuel Cooper in Washington, D.C., relate Hitchcock's experience in the Second Seminole War. An accompanying note indicates that the letters were returned from Cooper to Hitchcock in 1841.
  Letters from Ethan Allen Hitchcock to Secretary of War John C. Spencer relate to the return of documents that Hitchcock had copied, and to the Second Seminole War.
  Former call number: Uncat WA MSS 55
  - Diary of Thomas Sidney Jesup, 1836 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Letters from Ethan Allen Hitchcock to Major Samuel Cooper, 1840 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Letters from Ethan Allen Hitchcock to John C. Spencer (retained copies), 1842 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- 1992 Acquisitions, 1804-1896; 0.42; (2 boxes)
  Purchased from Goodspeed's Book Shop, Inc. on the Arthur Corbitt Hoskins Memorial Fund, 1992.
  Organized into folders based on geographic region or tribe, as received by the Beinecke Library.
  The acquisitions consist of correspondence, maps, reports, and notes relating to General Thomas Sidney Jesup, to General Ethan Allen Hitchcock, and to removal campaigns against Indians of the Southeast, including Seminole, Choctaw, Creek, and Cherokee.
  Correspondence includes three letters in the Choctaw language from the 1830s and 1840s (two written by Jonathan Cogswell), and one letter from a group of removed Creek Indians to the president of the United States, describing their journey to Indian Territory and requesting that the remainder of their tribe join them.
  Other letters are written by military personnel and Indian agents in Alabama, Florida, and elsewhere in the Southeast, and document removal activities and military relations with Southeastern Indian people (including the Creek War of 1836 led by Generals Thomas Sidney Jesup and Winfield Scott).
  Also included are rolls of children sent to boarding schools and of Indian people who were removed to Oklahoma, chiefly to Fort Gibson.
  The notebooks of General Ethan Allen Hitchcock record his research on the Creek Indians in 1842, in Canadian, Oklahoma.
  Manuscript maps document military activity and forts in Florida, and the Cherokee Reservation in Arkansas.
  Many letters are originals; others are manuscript copies.
  Former call numbers: Uncat WA MSS 146, Uncat WA MSS 147
  - Statement signed by Carlos Hernandez, Pedro Albe Roche___ and Francisco Barrios, 1804 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Seminole, 1837-1838, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Letter: Seminole Chiefs Holatoochee and Coocoochee (Wild Cat) to Alligator (Halpatter Tustennuggee), undated.
    Map of the territory around Micanopy and report of reconnaisance, undated.
    "List of Indian/Seminole prisoners turned over by Lt. Geo. H. [Jewitt?]," 1837.
    Letter: "Reynolds" to "Captain," Tampa Bay, Florida, 1838 May 2.
    Map of the territory between the Oscilla and Suwanee Rivers, undated.
    Diagram of Fort Micanopy, 1837.
    Letter: [Thomas Jesup?] to unidentified recipient relating to Cherokee Chief John Ross and Seminole Chief Alligator, undated.
  - Seminole, 1812-1838 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Letter: George Travers to Joseph Forrest, 1812 November 20.
    Financial records of Captain P. Morrison, relating to Seminole removal, 1837-1838.
    List of captured slaves, returned to Seminole owners, 1837 September 4.
  - Choctaw, Creek, and Cherokee, 1834-1869 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Letter: Willy Thompson to James W. Henderson, Tallahassee, Florida, 1834 January 27.
    "Description of the boundary of the reserve at Ford Gibson," B. Atwood, 1840.
    Letter: Jonathan Cogswell to Cyrus Byington, 1840 August 17. In Choctaw.
    Letter: John Bell to Abraham Martin, 1841 August 10.
    Letter: G. Hudson to unidentified recipient, 1842 September 26.
    Letter: John L. M. Coy to Henry Cunningham, 1845 May 26.
    Letter: [James McKinney?] to General Matthew Arbuckle, 1846 June 20.
    Letter: Reverend Samuel A. Worcester to Jefferson Davis, 1834 September 6.
    Letter: Asa C. Matthews to John Jumper, 1865 June 23.
    Declaration of the Cherokee National Council, 1865 July 14.
    Map of the Cherokee Reservation in Arkansas, undated.
    Letter: G. W. Stidham to "Major Fields," 1869 August 21. Includes an English translation of a letter from Samuel Checotee, Principal Chief Creek Nation, to G. W. Stidham, 1869 August 18.
  - Choctaw, Creek, 1833-1836 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Report of Lieutenant Colonel Many, 1833 July 4.
    List of boys sent from Talladega County, Alabama to the Choctaw Academy in Scott County Kentucky, 1834 September 28.
    Letter: Jonathan Cogswell to unidentified recipient, 1835 October 6. In Choctaw.
    Letter: William Miner to Needham Massie, 1836 August 7.
    Letter: J. Moore to John A. Campbell, 1836 September 12.
    Letter: C. A. Harris to Brevet Brigadier General M. Arbuckle, 1836 October 11.
    Letter: Muscogee Creek chiefs (Opothleyahola, Little Darter, Mad Blue, Tuckabatchee Micco) to Andrew Jackson, 1836 December 25.
  - "Florida Indians", 1836-1839, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    List of supplies received by J. H. Simpson, 1836.
    Letter: Reynolds to Captain P. Morrison, 1838 November 15.
    Letter: C. A. Harris to P. Morrison, 1837 September 7.
    Letter: P. Morrison to Thomas Jesup, 1837 October 14.
    Abstract of provisions issued by Captain P. Morrison, 1839.
    Letter: P. Morrison to C. A. Harris, 1838 May.
    Letter: Unidentified author to "Sir," 1837 November 30.
    Map of St. Andrews Bay region, undated.
  - Seminole, 1837 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Letter: Captain G. W. Allen to Colonel William S. Foster, 1837 February 10.
    Letter: John Page to "Sir," 1837 March 6.
    Letter: Unidentified author to Lieutenant Colonel J. B. Crane, 1837 March 27.
    Letter: James Bright to Hanson Kelly, 1837 May 8.
    Letter: [Chuccottee fiscico?] to Thomas Jesup, 1837 August 11.
    "Copy of instructions from John Ross to the Cherokee delegation to the Seminole Indians," 1837 October 20.
  - Ethan Allen Hitchcock Notebooks
    The notes record information from Mr. Alexander in Canadian, Oklahoma and from Mr. Edwards near the Little River, Oklahoma
    - "Creek laws abstracted", 1842 January (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - "Creeks", 1842 January 31 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - "Creeks", 1842 February 3 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - "Creeks, Chickasaws", 1842 February 13 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- 1994 Acquisition, 1836-1856; 0.21; (1 box)
  Purchased from William Reese Co. on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 1994.
  The acquisition consists of notes and correspondence relating to the Second Seminole War and to Indian removal generally. Includes an account by Thomas Sidney Jesup, autograph manuscript, relating the capture of Seminole chief Osceola.
  Existence and Location of Originals
  Former call number: Uncat WA MSS 174
  - Manuscript notebook listing 104 "principal chiefs" of Killagee Town, 1836 May 13 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Letter: John W. Moore to Governor C. C. Clay of Alabama, 1836 June 11 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Statement: Bird Culbertson, relating to the chief Neah Micco, 1836 June 12 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Letter: H. W. Russell and others to General Thomas Jesup., 1836 June 28 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Statement: Seven Indian scouts, relating to leaving service, 1836 June 25 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Letter: R. B. [Sawen?] to Captain Page, 1836 August 31 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Letter: C. C. Clay to William D. Pickett, 1836 July 9 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Letter: Lieutenant J. P. Sloan to unidentified recipient, 1837 March 31 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Letter: Jonathan G. Reynolds to Major [Whiting?], 1837 March 31 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Letter: Capt. Samuel Ringgold to Major L. Whiting, 1837 May 22 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Letter: Major Wilson to Major General Thomas Jesup, 1837 June 16 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Letter: Unidentified author to Major General Thomas Jesup, 1837 July 27 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Churchill, Major S., Measurements of roads in south Alabama and Georgia, 1837 July 31 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Letter: Captain Patrick Galt to Major General Thomas Jesup, 1837 August 15 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Opothleyahola, Promissory note for $1000, 1837 August 26 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - John Ross, manuscript copy of an address, 1837 October 18 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Gibbs, K. B., transcript of a conversation between Major General Thomas Jesup and Seminole chiefs, including Osceola, 1837 October 21 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Letter: Thomas Jefferson Smith to Major General Thomas Jesup, 1838 January 12 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - August, Manuscript statement of "August, a Seminole Negro, in relation to the representations and promises of the Cherokee delegation to the Seminole Chiefs", 1838 February 18 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Letter: General C. H. Nelson to General Lewis A. Armistead, 1838 March 11 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Letter: Eleven Creek chiefs to unidentified recipients, 1839 January 5 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Letter: William N. Anderson to Colonel S. H. Sevier, 1839 November 19 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Manuscript petition to General Lewis A. Armistead from "inhabitants bordering on the OKefe Noke [sic]", 1840 August 25 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Letter: W. L. McClintock to Colonel Gates, 1840 December 31 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Letter: William P. Duval to Major General Thomas Jesup, 1842 October 4 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Letter: William Armstrong to merchants in Arkansas, 1844 August (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Manuscript bill of sale signed by Seminole chiefs Jumper and Wild Cat, 1849 January 11 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Letter: Marcellus Duval to Coocoochee (Wild Cat), 1849 September 9 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Letter: William Bowlegs to Jim Jumper, 1850 April 12 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - "Statement made to Captain J. Brauman U.S.A. by the chiefs of the Indian delegation (taken to Florida from Arkansas) by Luther Blake ...", 1853 January (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Letter: W. M. Gardner to General Ethan Allen Hitchcock, 1856 February 23 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Major General Thomas Jesup, autograph manuscript account of the capture of Osceola, 1858 (Box 5, Folder 51)